[SPEAKER_01]: I was wondering if we could speak about lying, the phenomenon of lying, the choice to lie.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, a simple question, is it wrong to lie?
[SPEAKER_01]: You know, where can we go with that?
[SPEAKER_00]: Sure, sure.
[SPEAKER_00]: It is.
[SPEAKER_00]: So now you can ask, why is it wrong to lie?
[SPEAKER_00]: As in, don't just take it as an authority who declared that lying is wrong and now you must obey by it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, lying is wrong, but you want to investigate why it is wrong.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, what's the first, most obvious thing that shows itself if you start to investigate why lying would be wrong?
[SPEAKER_00]: What is lying?
[SPEAKER_01]: Dishonesty.
[SPEAKER_00]: Dishonesty.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, okay, so what are, like, dishonesty, lying, concealing, what all those things have in common?
[SPEAKER_01]: You're not wanting something to be known.
[SPEAKER_00]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which means, something is, but you want to be different.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, in its nature, it's a... it's a... it's a... it's a discrepancy.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's a fundamental... it's a contradiction.
[SPEAKER_00]: The two opposing things.
[SPEAKER_00]: One is the truth.
[SPEAKER_00]: The other one is what you would prefer to be.
[SPEAKER_00]: But the problem with lying is, phenomenologically speaking, from a point... from a point of view of a person who practices mindfulness, trance, level of wisdom, the problem of lying is that you can't... you cannot deny the truth without implying that... without giving importance to your point of view over the truth.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's why lying is practically wrong.
[SPEAKER_00]: Lying is practically an obstacle.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you could say, theoretically, lie without perverting that existential order of truth and my point of view, then lying would not be unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_00]: But it is impossible to engage in an act of lying without implicitly, immediately, eh... fueling the wrong order whereby
[SPEAKER_00]: It's my point of view, my preference, that comes first.
[SPEAKER_00]: Truth is second.
[SPEAKER_00]: And when I say truth, I mean factual presence of a self-realism phenomena.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's the key here.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not like the truth.
[SPEAKER_00]: There is a lie and then there is a truth.
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: You denying, well, you denying that whatever the truth is at the time, by serving a lie,
[SPEAKER_00]: Means you implicitly also overriding the the most self-evident basic nature of the arisen experience, that it comes first, structurally first.
[SPEAKER_00]: Your point of view is structurally second.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, by engaging in a lie, you're engaging in perversion of that order.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why even a little lie is as bad as a bad lie, as a big lie.
[SPEAKER_00]: From the point of view of the mind that wants to practice, because practice means undoing any perversion to the existential order of the five aggregates.
[SPEAKER_00]: In the same sense, like, you cannot engage in a sensual act without sensual perceptions being implied.
[SPEAKER_00]: And sensual perceptions are sensual distortions.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, in other words, you can't engage in sensuality without having
[SPEAKER_00]: Without being distorted by sensuality at the same time, without fueling already persisting distortion of central perception.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you can't engage in a lie without fueling the existential distortion, basically, of the arisen phenomenon, the truth, the self-evident arising of whatever is present.
[SPEAKER_00]: The arisen experience is there on its own.
[SPEAKER_00]: Means my attitude, my actions upon it, are only because this thing allows my actions to be a possibility.
[SPEAKER_00]: In other words, if there is no, say, unpleasant feeling manifested, would you be even able to conceive acting out of an unpleasant feeling, to try to get rid of it?
[SPEAKER_00]: You wouldn't.
[SPEAKER_00]: Or on a less fundamental level, if there's something like, I don't know, take some experience,
[SPEAKER_00]: You have to go to work.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's your reason situation that persists there, that has its significance, like things you have to do, reasons why you have to do it, because you need to earn money, you need to do this, you need to provide.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's your factual situation.
[SPEAKER_00]: On account of it, you'll be acting left and right, and so on, and deciding.
[SPEAKER_00]: But when you start engaging in an act of lying,
[SPEAKER_00]: You're overriding that very order.
[SPEAKER_00]: Doesn't mean you can change the order.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, there's still things that risen on their own, but you are fully gratuitously giving priority to your point of view, that in itself, at that time, is based on that simply on ignoring what the real order is.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, in other words, you start lying about having to go to work.
[SPEAKER_00]: Lying to yourself, not even lying to others.
[SPEAKER_00]: You start saying, no, you don't need to go to work, because really you don't want to go to work.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you start lying, because the reason thing is unbearable, or not necessarily unbearable, but it's unpleasant and you don't want to have to deal with it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's why another aspect of an act of lying is, it's always rooted in avoiding displeasure.
[SPEAKER_00]: Why else would you be lying?
[SPEAKER_00]: Unless you yourself perceive that if you don't admit the truth, you will avoid that displeasure, the pain of that truth.
[SPEAKER_00]: But can you really avoid the pain?
[SPEAKER_00]: Through sort of looking elsewhere?
[SPEAKER_00]: You can't.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're only acting out of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, you're looking elsewhere because it's there.
[SPEAKER_00]: Exactly, exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, see, the fact that you engaged in an act of lie means you do have, you have, you, well, you had it before and now you're maintaining the belief that you can avoid the arisen pressure of the truth.
[SPEAKER_00]: That this pleasure of the truth simply by lying.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which then means, implies, that you can avoid existentially arisen phenomena simply by providing another phenomena.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's fundamentally rooted... act of lying is fundamentally rooted in a wrong view.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why it's fundamentally unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_00]: And it's the same with any of the precepts that the Buddha laid out.
[SPEAKER_00]: None of them are, like, universally given commandments.
[SPEAKER_00]: All of them are rooted in the principle of greed, aversion, delusion, which, separately, individually, are all also principles of some form of contradicting the arisen nature of experience, which is why it's unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_00]: They're not unwholesome because it's a... it's a universal morality applied to it.
[SPEAKER_00]: They're unwholesome because they go against how things have arisen.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's how you can know for yourself that they're unwholesome, once you understand the nature of things, how they have arisen.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, then you have a criteria for what's... what's skillful, what's unskillful, what's wholesome, what's unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's why lying is always wrong.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because it always goes against the principle, against the nature of an arisen thing, whatever that thing is.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the example we gave, eh... you don't want to go and do this particular work, now you can admit that.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can... you don't have to lie to yourself, but that means now you have to take responsibility for the... this pleasure you're feeling.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, the work needs to be done, but I choose not to, which means all the reasons they were making me do this work,
[SPEAKER_00]: Supporting my family, earning, whatever else necessary, whatever else was the motivation for working, I'm now responsible for not meeting any of those requirements.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, when down the line circumstances remind me of that, my family starts asking for money, or I get sick and I can't pay for my treatment and so on,
[SPEAKER_00]: It's because I chose to not do this particular work.
[SPEAKER_00]: So I'm responsible for that.
[SPEAKER_00]: So now, this future misfortune that came as a result of not being able to look after yourself, is because you chose not to look after yourself.
[SPEAKER_00]: There's nothing wrong with that.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's the thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: You have every right to choose to know.
[SPEAKER_00]: But that means you must take responsibility for what comes out of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: But now that means, oh,
[SPEAKER_00]: By trying to avoid the responsibility of doing my duty, for example, now I'm actually paying the price, which is even worse.
[SPEAKER_00]: Now I can't provide for the family, I don't have enough money for this, I don't have enough money for that, I don't have enough money for food, and da-da-da-da-da-da.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's on you.
[SPEAKER_00]: Result of your choice to avoid work.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's very unpleasant.
[SPEAKER_00]: You have to admit that it's on you.
[SPEAKER_00]: So now all this... and it can endure for weeks and months, for what?
[SPEAKER_00]: For as long as you don't get out of that situation.
[SPEAKER_00]: But it's still a responsible thing to do.
[SPEAKER_00]: Admit the weight of your choices.
[SPEAKER_00]: But it's way too easy to not admit it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Only, if only, you find another reason for you not doing the work, apart from you not wanting to do the work.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's the nature of bad faith and existential philosophy, which is like
[SPEAKER_00]: It's like lying, but not quite lying, because you're not necessarily fully self-aware of the truth, because it's the very truth you're trying to cover up for yourself.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, now, if I say, well, I couldn't work because of such and such... whatever... things came... like, I couldn't work because it was raining.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not like, oh, I couldn't work because I chose rain to be the reason for my not working.
[SPEAKER_00]: But if you say, you know, it was raining, so I couldn't work, which means now, when I don't have enough money, it's because it's the weather's fault.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you bypass responsibility for not working at the time, and then, consequently, for all the future issues that came out, that there were results of not working, are also bypassed.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because, see, it's not on me.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why people always, inherently, it's the easiest thing to blame another, or to blame circumstances.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's that inauthentic attitude we speak about often in in our videos.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because unless you take responsibility on that fundamental level, you'll never have a basis for dhamma to apply.
[SPEAKER_00]: And fundamental responsibility is suffering.
[SPEAKER_00]: Again, like, you don't want to work because it's unpleasant.
[SPEAKER_00]: You don't want to accept future responsibility for the consequences of your not working because it's unpleasant.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, fundamentally, you don't want to suffer and you keep avoiding displeasure as the only mean of dealing with suffering that you know.
[SPEAKER_00]: But it doesn't deal with it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Evading suffering can only be done because suffering has arisen.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's the truth.
[SPEAKER_00]: Displeasure is manifested and you're liable to future manifestation of displeasure.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's the truth that you will never understand, because all your actions revolve around avoiding that very truth.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, lying to other people is just extension of this very principle.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you can't undo that principle, as in lying to yourself, unless you stop habitually lying to other people.
[SPEAKER_00]: But stopping to... stopping... ceasing to lie to other people doesn't necessarily mean you will automatically undo lying to yourself.
[SPEAKER_00]: That takes a further effort.
[SPEAKER_00]: But that further effort is only possible on the basis of the first effort of stop lying to others.
[SPEAKER_00]: Stop proliferate... stop maintaining, basically,
[SPEAKER_00]: Stop proliferating that wrong order of things through your acts of lying to others, so you reduce it a bit, and then you will be able to stop lying to yourself as well.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's how you can accept responsibility.
[SPEAKER_00]: And suffering, as I said, is a fundamental responsibility.
[SPEAKER_00]: See, you can say, oh, I suffer because he said this.
[SPEAKER_00]: Or I suffer because I didn't get enough, or I suffer because, you know, I lost my family or something like that.
[SPEAKER_00]: And if those things were truly rooted in... sorry, if suffering was truly rooted in those things, yeah, you wouldn't be able to be free from it.
[SPEAKER_00]: But as the Buddha himself understood and then told to others, it... fortunately, it isn't rooted in those things.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's rooted in your resistance of the disagreeable things that come your way.
[SPEAKER_00]: But those are two different things.
[SPEAKER_00]: But for as long as your actions maintain the view that it's in the things, in what he said, or she said, or what I had, what I lost, you will never take responsibility for suffering.
[SPEAKER_00]: As in, you will never take responsibility for your resistance to the disagreeable experience.
[SPEAKER_00]: And because of that, you will always remain affected by the disagreeable experience.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the only way to stop resisting disagreeable experience is to take responsibility for the disagreeable experience.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not lie to yourself.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not lie to yourself.
[SPEAKER_00]: Consequently, you won't be lying to others.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why Arhat cannot lie.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's because he became incapable of lying to himself where the problem is, because he solved the problem.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes, the key is don't lie to yourself.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: But in order to not lie to yourself, you have to stop habitually lying to others.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, what about these common white lines?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, again, like...
[SPEAKER_00]: It doesn't look so bad.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's not as bad, but you have to be strict and you have to see, does it partake in the principle of lying, principle you're trying to undo, principle of perverting the order of existence, putting the blame where the blame isn't.
[SPEAKER_00]: And if you look at the white lies and stuff, yeah, it's still perverting.
[SPEAKER_00]: Why would you white lying?
[SPEAKER_00]: Because you don't want discomfort.
[SPEAKER_00]: Why you don't want discomfort?
[SPEAKER_00]: Because you're blaming discomfort for pain.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which means, by not wanting discomfort, you're avoiding the responsibility for resisting the discomfort.
[SPEAKER_00]: And blaming the discomfort for your suffering.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, I'll just white lie quickly, so I don't get discomfort means I won't suffer.
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: You don't suffer when you don't resist.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not that you don't suffer when there is no discomfort.
[SPEAKER_00]: Arahant has discomfort, he has no suffering.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's why white lies are bad.
[SPEAKER_01]: And to... and if you... if you could save somebody from suffering, future...
[SPEAKER_01]: By lying... Where is this person hiding?
[SPEAKER_01]: You know, these people are looking for this.
[SPEAKER_00]: Right, right, right, right.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, fundamentally, you're always... On the most fundamental level, reasons for your action are always selfish.
[SPEAKER_00]: It cannot be otherwise.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, you choose to help others, because that's what's going to make you happy.
[SPEAKER_00]: Or you choose to help others, because that's how you're going to avoid personal discomfort.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, others are always secondary.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's not going...
[SPEAKER_00]: The only way to go about this, is to accept it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, stop perverting the order, as we... as we just spoke about.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, stop blaming the circumstances for your suffering.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, recognize that it's in you resisting the circumstances, that's where suffering is rooted.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, when, like, you're hiding a fugitive or something,
[SPEAKER_00]: And then you lie to others, like, no, I don't know where that person is.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, you're saving their life, maybe, if that's at stake, I don't know, but what you're really acting out of is you being responsible for choosing to sort of have them in the first place and then, secondly, for not wanting to experience this comfort of responsibility.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because if you say the truth, they'll find that person and then things might happen to the person and you will be unable
[SPEAKER_00]: To not blame yourself.
[SPEAKER_00]: And blaming yourself, it's unpleasant.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, really, you just want to prevent circumstances to allow you to engage in self-blaming.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you're doing it for yourself.
[SPEAKER_00]: But that's what Buddha said in the suttas.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's often mentioned, like, if a person who is truthful to himself, truthful to others,
[SPEAKER_00]: If he's questioned by kings or authorities, have you seen this?
[SPEAKER_00]: He will say, yes, I've seen it.
[SPEAKER_00]: If he hasn't seen it, he'll say, no, I haven't seen it.
[SPEAKER_00]: He won't say one or the other for no one's sake.
[SPEAKER_00]: He'll say the truth.
[SPEAKER_00]: Why?
[SPEAKER_00]: Because you say the truth.
[SPEAKER_00]: And if these people that are chasing that fugitive choose to do certain things with that fugitive, that's not on you.
[SPEAKER_00]: Even if you say, yes, he went into that house.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's not on you.
[SPEAKER_00]: What they choose to do with him.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, why or to what extent?
[SPEAKER_00]: That's not on you.
[SPEAKER_00]: On you is to not pervert the existential order from your point of view.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because by doing so, you're giving priority to your point of view, which means it's a slippery slope.
[SPEAKER_00]: You act out of avoiding discomfort, means you're going to be acting out of prolonging pleasure, which means you're going to be acting out of conceit, out of delusion, out of... And that, those are the reasons for your own suffering, not the circumstances you've been subjected to.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, basically, practically, through trying to avoid suffering, you end up making yourself more and more liable to suffering on that existential level.
[SPEAKER_01]: Hence, no lying, no stealing, no cheating, no killing.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not negotiable.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because without that basis, you cannot overcome
[SPEAKER_00]: the attitude of avoiding responsibility for your own existence and for your own suffering.
[SPEAKER_00]: You just can't, even if you want to.
[SPEAKER_01]: There's a major offense for a monk if he lies about, you know, having attained a superior state.
[SPEAKER_01]: He lies about his wisdom.
[SPEAKER_01]: Why is that, you know?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, because the consequences of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like the results of your action, that's why.
[SPEAKER_01]: People take what you say as truth.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: And it can spread for generations.
[SPEAKER_00]: And people will then be acting out of that as the truth, while in reality it isn't the truth.
[SPEAKER_00]: In other words, as the Buddha described in some other suttas, you know, like giving to an enlightened being, making offering to like somebody who is factually awakened and free from suffering, is the greatest merit.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if somebody is factually, or there is a word that such and such is factually free from suffering, he's an arahant, oh, I'll quickly go and make some merit, because giving to that person is going to have much more merit than giving to just any anybody else who isn't enlightened.
[SPEAKER_00]: If that's the truth, you will actually get all those results, that great merit, because the person is factually an arahant.
[SPEAKER_00]: Let's say somebody spreads a lie that he's an arahant.
[SPEAKER_00]: And nobody knows it's a lie.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then people go out of their way, and they don't give to others, because they want to give to this arahant.
[SPEAKER_00]: And in reality, he isn't an arahant.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the whole mess created was because somebody lied that that person is an arahant.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, as a direct result of that lie, millions have been misguided.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, many people have been misguided.
[SPEAKER_00]: And they've been acting as if that person is an arahant,
[SPEAKER_00]: Being sure they're going to get all this merit, dedicating all the offerings to that one person, because he's not... and it turns out he isn't.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, they've been deceived directly as a result of that lie, which means the person who lied is going to be responsible for that mass deception cause, which can, as I said, can last for generations.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's why it's bad.
[SPEAKER_01]: You say that a monk could be deceiving himself.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which then deceives others.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, but that's different.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why, like, that's why it's not an offense, if a monk does that out of overestimation.
[SPEAKER_01]: He thinks, I know the way out.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's what I meant when I said, like, lying to others, it's not quite on the same level as lying to yourself, because lying to yourself means obscuring the truth.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, simply through obscuring the truth, you're lying to yourself.
[SPEAKER_00]: But when you come to lie to others, means you're fully aware of what truth is being obscured.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then you act completely the opposite way.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's an extra layer.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's why the attitude of bad faith, avoiding responsibility, it's not like fully fledged as lying to another person.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because in order to lie, you need to know what the truth is.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can't lie if you think what you're saying is the truth.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: But when it comes to yourself, it's not that clear-cut.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because you're already refusing to admit what the truth is.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you're refusing to be fully aware of what the truth is.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which means, you can't, like, fully lie to yourself.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because in order to fully lie to yourself, you need to fully admit the truth to yourself.
[SPEAKER_00]: But lying to yourself, it's not on the level of actually lying to yourself, but it's on a level of repressing or pressing, like turning away, ignoring the truth.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why Vijaya is ignorance.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not like a...
[SPEAKER_00]: metaphysical lack of information of what the universe is.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's ignoring what's right in front of you.
[SPEAKER_00]: And lying to others comes on the on the basis of that principle.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's just further proliferated.
[SPEAKER_00]: And it's the sustaining of the thing that you... Oh, yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Someone said, quote someone, lying is the lifeblood of addiction.
[SPEAKER_00]: Sure, sure.
[SPEAKER_00]: But you could say that
[SPEAKER_00]: Lifeblood of lying is avoiding self... is avoiding responsibility for your own experience.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, basically, the basis for lying is... is attitude of bad faith to yourself, as in having faith in ignoring, not in what you're actually ignoring.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's what I mean, you pervert the order.
[SPEAKER_00]: The only way you can ignore something is because it's there.
[SPEAKER_00]: But you focus on prioritizing the act of ignoring, not the act of what's already there.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's the most fundamental attitude towards the experience, the avijja, turning a blind eye.
[SPEAKER_00]: The only way you can turn a blind eye to something is if that thing is already there.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the most fundamental attitudes of turning a blind eye
[SPEAKER_00]: Is that fundamental wrong view in regard to the nature of existence?
[SPEAKER_00]: Being...
[SPEAKER_00]: I'm not my own, as in, I'm not in control of this, of this body upon which my whole life depends.
[SPEAKER_00]: I'm subject to aging, I'm subject to death, suffering.
[SPEAKER_00]: All these things are obvious.
[SPEAKER_00]: But the only reason people do not resolve them is because they give priority to ignoring them.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's what I mean.
[SPEAKER_00]: You give priority to your point of view on account of what's there in regard to which you exercise your point of view.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's why ignoring the ignorance, it's like a vicious circle.
[SPEAKER_00]: Avijja leads to more avijja.
[SPEAKER_00]: Ignoring leads to maintenance of the attitude of ignoring.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, what do I need to stop ignoring then, to undo the entire avijja of the whole saṃsāra?
[SPEAKER_00]: Stop ignoring the arisen feelings.
[SPEAKER_00]: Stop ignoring the reasoned intentions.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's why person who has made that effort and stopped ignoring these things will become incapable of engaging in ill-will, anger, lying, cheating, even sensuality.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because sensuality in itself, it's already that perversion on the fundamental level.
[SPEAKER_00]: Finding pleasurable in that which is truly ugly.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you ignore that it's ugly.
[SPEAKER_00]: Ignorance of the ugly is the basis for attraction.
[SPEAKER_00]: Ignoring the ugly.
[SPEAKER_01]: The unattractive.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Ignoring the unattractiveness.
[SPEAKER_00]: The fundamental unattractiveness.
[SPEAKER_00]: The fundamental kind of dispassion.
[SPEAKER_00]: Or absence of passion in it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Ignoring that is how you have maintained passion in it.
[SPEAKER_01]: What's the nature of concealment?
[SPEAKER_00]: I suppose, eh... Well, in this... in the suttas, and often, you know, in many of them, in the Buddhist writings, you often hear about delusion, greed, aversion, delusion.
[SPEAKER_01]: Lova, dosa and moha.
[SPEAKER_01]: So,
[SPEAKER_00]: You know, people can get their head around greed, can get their head around aversion, but often delusion is kind of regarded as something that's not directly my responsibility, inasmuch as greed is, or aversion.
[SPEAKER_01]: I don't know what I don't know.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's regarded in a sort of a semi-metaphysical sense, as in, it's there, but it's not really something I can directly experience.
[SPEAKER_00]: But actually, it is.
[SPEAKER_00]: Delusion is an attitude of your mind in as much greed or lust and aversion are.
[SPEAKER_00]: Otherwise, you wouldn't have been mentioned always like that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Right.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, from that point of view, delusion, it's more of like an attitude of indolence, laziness,
[SPEAKER_01]: Choice to keep things cloudy.
[SPEAKER_00]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: Keeping it opaque intentionally.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not look... turning a blind eye.
[SPEAKER_00]: Distracting yourself intentionally with things that are going to take your mind away from yourself.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you realize delusion is a very active thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: And, as the Buddha said, that's why it's the most blameworthy, actually.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because it's the hardest to undo as well.
[SPEAKER_00]: But the fact that you can undo it, means it's not this metaphysical lack of knowledge.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's your very attitude.
[SPEAKER_00]: That it's even more fundamental than the attitude of lust and the attitude of aversion.
[SPEAKER_01]: They're kind of secondary to it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Lust requires a basis of delusion.
[SPEAKER_00]: Aversion requires a basis of delusion.
[SPEAKER_00]: Delusion requires a basis of delusion.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you're deluded through and through, not because you don't know certain things, but because you perpetually act
[SPEAKER_00]: Out of ignorance, that then maintains yourself in the situation of ignorance.
[SPEAKER_00]: And situation of ignorance, again, it's not ignorance-ignorance, as in you don't know something.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's you actively ignoring and giving priority to the ignoring of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, choosing is... choosing to distract yourself, for example.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, actively, actively making a choice,
[SPEAKER_00]: They will result in certain actions.
[SPEAKER_00]: They're not necessarily lustful or hateful, but are based upon, you know, wanting to be self-aware, for example.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, entertainment or distraction in general.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, I'm bored by myself, because I'm aware of everything.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's very unpleasant.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, I just go and chat to some people, randomly.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not for sensual reasons or because I hate them, just because I want something to do.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, often, needing things to do is rooted in delusion, as in distraction, as in indolence, on the level of... Like, you can be very diligent externally, he's doing all this work, but the reasons for you doing that work are rooted in you wanting to turn a blind eye in regard to yourself.
[SPEAKER_00]: You don't want to be self-aware, basically.
[SPEAKER_01]: You don't want to see the truth of your mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, yeah, because that will result in the unpleasant truths of your mind, or simply unpleasant states of boredom and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, I better find something to do.
[SPEAKER_00]: I better find an external purpose.
[SPEAKER_00]: It will occupy my mind, so my mind won't be aware of itself, because being aware of itself is too unpleasant.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's too threatening.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's a way of keep covering up the truth.
[SPEAKER_00]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's the way of maintaining yourself in a state of cover-up.
[SPEAKER_01]: Keep the dust moving.
[SPEAKER_00]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: Otherwise, if it settles, you get to see what's there and it's unpleasant.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's the thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: You say self-aware.
[SPEAKER_01]: It sounds like a good thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it's like the most painful thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: It is, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Things most people avoid.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, that's why solitude is very unpleasant to begin with.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why, as the Buddha himself said many times, he practices so you develop the pleasure of solitude.
[SPEAKER_00]: You won't get it right away.
[SPEAKER_00]: If done rightly, it's unpleasant.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because you're going against the against the grain of all the distraction you got used to it and that your existence depends upon.
[SPEAKER_00]: But that's it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, when you get into like... when you stop maintaining all these attitudes of... they were based upon obscuring the self-awareness.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, when you stop feeding those attitudes, the self-awareness increases.
[SPEAKER_00]: But it feels like
[SPEAKER_00]: You know, the boredom starts giving rise to dread and anxiety.
[SPEAKER_00]: Feels like you yourself are drowning.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's crushing you.
[SPEAKER_00]: But what is actually crushing is your assumed level of your own being, the one that you've been proliferating.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not actually crushing you.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like being alone in your room, not seeing or talking to anyone, cannot do anything to you.
[SPEAKER_00]: But yeah, your mind can sort of drown in it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because the mind became dependent upon a certain degree of engagement with the world.
[SPEAKER_00]: That is its threshold.
[SPEAKER_00]: But that's not a static thing, that threshold.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which means, the more you engage, the more dependent upon engagement you become.
[SPEAKER_00]: The less engaged, well, initially, it might hurt the lesser engagement, because you used to engage more, but then you get used to that.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then it will not be unpleasant.
[SPEAKER_00]: In the same sense, like you have a very hectic person, who's been sort of doing a lot, engaging a lot, working a lot, for whatever reasons, and then, if he was made to sit down and stop engaging to that level, the discrepancy would be just too much to handle.
[SPEAKER_00]: But if he gradually starts doing that, and then starts ceasing his engagement, he'll get used to that new level of lacking the engagement that he used to have.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which means, you are responsible for the threshold of where your being is.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's when it says, his consciousness gets established upon that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, that becomes the norm, that becomes what you're used to it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which means, anything less than that, it's gonna fill you with anxiety and dread.
[SPEAKER_00]: But it's important to recognize that it's not a static thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, through... through using engagement,
[SPEAKER_00]: With the world, actions, meaningless work, whatever else, or not even finding meaning for your work, whatever.
[SPEAKER_00]: Practically, you're engaging with the world for the means of escaping self-awareness.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you will become dependent on that level of engagement.
[SPEAKER_00]: Anything less than that engagement will bring you back to your self-awareness.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that means, then, you have to keep maintaining the level of your engagement and, once you get used to it, you have to keep increasing it, if you try to use it to avoid self-awareness.
[SPEAKER_00]: And most people, to a degree, are using that.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why most people are afraid to be alone.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not afraid from, like, some, you know, monsters and stuff, but afraid just, in broad daylight, being left alone in their room for a whole day, without doing anything, without taking my mind away from myself.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why most people would be afraid to be left alone.
[SPEAKER_00]: It would result in experiencing anxiety and existential dread.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because the human life, on average, is about avoiding that self-awareness, which ties in with avoiding irresponsibility and feeds one another and so on.
[SPEAKER_01]: But that self-awareness is the thing that's going to make things right.
[SPEAKER_00]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why people are, because of their own actions, they're liable to suffering.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because of that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not because of some
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not someone else's fault or some design.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's because you act in a manner that keeps making you liable to suffer, keeps you exposed.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you could then...
[SPEAKER_00]: If you take responsibility for it, that's where what I'm saying might become apparent.
[SPEAKER_00]: That the level of engagement, the level of distraction, the level of turning a blind eye, it's not a static thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which means you can...
[SPEAKER_00]: The way you've been kind of proliferating it, you can then also undo it, if you stop engaging with it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Or you can certainly put a brakes on its growth.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why the bhāva in the suttas being... Again, it's not a metaphysical thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's the level of your dependence on the senses, which is central being.
[SPEAKER_00]: The level of dependence on the sense of the world, the duty,
[SPEAKER_00]: The perception thing you perceive around the level you depend on it.
[SPEAKER_00]: But then you can start depending less.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why Arahant has cessation of his being.
[SPEAKER_00]: He doesn't depend on anything.
[SPEAKER_00]: But he's still there.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not that the being means destruction.
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: Being means assumption.
[SPEAKER_00]: Assumption of engagement, assumption of avoiding responsibility, assumption of sensuality.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's what delusion is.
[SPEAKER_00]: Ignoring, turning a blind eye, distracting yourself, not being able to live with yourself.
[SPEAKER_00]: And again, you can ask back onto that practical level that we always do.
[SPEAKER_00]: Why is it that I don't want to be self-aware?
[SPEAKER_00]: Why is it that I need to distract myself from myself?
[SPEAKER_00]: Because it's unpleasant.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, why am I then
[SPEAKER_00]: Maintaining this whole level of being for which I'm responsible, level of how much I depend on engagement with things.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, it's because I don't want to suffer.
[SPEAKER_01]: But failing to see that my very engagement is...
[SPEAKER_00]: It's the root of your suffering.
[SPEAKER_00]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, why do I suffer then?
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, it's because I keep running away from suffering.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why I suffer.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if I stop running away from suffering, I at least have a chance to not suffer.
[SPEAKER_01]: There was an example I heard, that people in prison...
[SPEAKER_01]: In prison, punishment is solitary confinement.
[SPEAKER_01]: And a lot of people would rather spend their time with other criminals, rapists or murderers, than be alone.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, it's not accidental that, yeah, that was always the worst punishment.
[SPEAKER_00]: Solitary confinement for prolonged periods of time.
[SPEAKER_00]: For an untrained mind, of course.
[SPEAKER_01]: You would rather do things that are bad for you.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: You would rather expose yourself to, like, genuine existential risks, than be alone with yourself.
[SPEAKER_01]: I jump out of a plane.
[SPEAKER_01]: I take a parachuting.
[SPEAKER_01]: I put my life on the line.
[SPEAKER_01]: I've got to do all these extreme sports, maybe.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: You know, just to avoid... Just to avoid, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, that's for me.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not a stationary thing, which means...
[SPEAKER_00]: Avoiding boredom needs to be maintained.
[SPEAKER_00]: Boredom sets in when you get used to the threshold.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, you need to do more.
[SPEAKER_00]: Same with sensuality.
[SPEAKER_00]: If people use sensuality as means of escape, if people get angry as means of escape, that's why you keep getting angrier and angrier as the life goes by.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because you keep getting used to it, and it ceases to work.
[SPEAKER_00]: Your means of escape cease to work, so then you need to keep running harder.
[SPEAKER_01]: The truth is always there.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's always kind of pushing up against you.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the fact, yeah, the fact that you give in to the attitude of ignoring the truth that's always there, means you're just running around in a circle.
[SPEAKER_00]: You don't really ever run away from... And everybody knows that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, if you ask any random person, even not familiar with Buddhism,
[SPEAKER_00]: Can you satisfy your sensual desires?
[SPEAKER_00]: Most people already know you can't, really.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can't satisfy them.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can only run around them.
[SPEAKER_00]: Same with anger.
[SPEAKER_00]: Is the satisfaction of revenge or inflicting pain back onto somebody, is that really preventing you from experiencing in the first place?
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: You know that.
[SPEAKER_00]: You just can't help it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you can't help it because you keep ignoring the truth.
[SPEAKER_00]: You keep ignoring the nature of what's right in front of you.
[SPEAKER_00]: Hence, ignoring will automatically, inevitably, result in lust and aversion, in greed and anger and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: But that doesn't mean that, you know, if you lock yourself in the room and stop engaging with the world, that you will automatically arrive at the right understanding either.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because it's a sad thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why the Buddha's instruction was necessary.
[SPEAKER_00]: Or the instruction of somebody externally who has done it themselves right away.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the two outcomes for somebody who hasn't... who doesn't have that external instruction, the two outcomes would be... Yeah, the only two outcomes basically would be possible, if they were to, say, lock themselves in.
[SPEAKER_00]: Either madness, as in the mind, would implode, because you wouldn't know the way out of itself, or you would develop a degree of that self-transparency and undo a great level of your being, which means become more transparent, less subjected to suffering, but you have to give in to something.
[SPEAKER_00]: You wouldn't be able to, like, remain... maintain that transparency all the way to the core of your being, whereby you've undone every single
[SPEAKER_00]: slightest of existential discrepancies, or slightest of the conceits, as the Buddha called them, and become an arahant.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because if you do that, you would be, like, self-enlightened.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, theoretically, it's possible, but practically, it's highly unlikely.
[SPEAKER_00]: But that doesn't mean that you shouldn't even try.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, even... even a person who is not necessarily interested in becoming fully enlightened and following the Buddha's instruction to the end, he would do it in good.
[SPEAKER_00]: If they start withdrawing the level, or keeping in check the level of their engagement and dependence on the world and the senses... Why?
[SPEAKER_00]: Because the life will end in you losing that dependence, through sickness, aging and death, losing your senses, losing the perception of the world, losing the things upon which your existence depends, or rather, things you used to maintain the level of being, that sort of help you to ignore
[SPEAKER_00]: If the life were truly to last forever, and you will always stay in the control of your senses, yeah, that's fine.
[SPEAKER_00]: No problem.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can do it.
[SPEAKER_00]: But it isn't.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you know that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Everybody knows that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yet, you act like you will live forever.
[SPEAKER_00]: And the more you're dependent on the senses, they will disappear and break apart, the more you'll be affected, when that happens.
[SPEAKER_00]: The less you're dependent, the less you'll be affected, means less you'll suffer.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's like the simile Buddha gave, climbing the tree to eat the mangoes, and eventually, somebody is bound to come down, come up, and cut that tree, because they can't climb the tree and eat the mangoes.
[SPEAKER_00]: Or even if they don't, the mangoes will age and break down, and the tree will fall.
[SPEAKER_00]: The higher you were climbed on that tree,
[SPEAKER_00]: The harder you will crash, the more suffering you will experience.
[SPEAKER_00]: But if you kept yourself in check and stay maybe with lower branches, if you couldn't help yourself but climb the tree in the first place, then at least kept yourself in check, use your reason, self-reflection to not proliferate too far out.
[SPEAKER_00]: In practical terms, you kept yourself in check how much you depend on distraction, how much you depend on other people, other people's company, how much you depend on gratuitous health,
[SPEAKER_00]: Senses, ability to access the world and so on and distract yourself with it.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you reflected on it, you will keep yourself in check and then don't go too... won't go too far in it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So then, when you do get sick, when your senses do start to fail, when people leave you or die or don't do what you want to do, you won't be as affected.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because you haven't made yourself as dependent.
[SPEAKER_00]: But if you are, you know, you have concealed so much your whole life... Well, if you concealed so much your whole life, it's never too late to start undoing that concealment.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's really the problem there.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you never start undoing your own... concealing basically yourself from yourself, concealing the nature of yourself from yourself... You've never actually faced displeasure.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Never admitted it where it is, where the problem of it is.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why people are responsible for being bound to saṃsāra.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not saṃsāra that binds you.
[SPEAKER_00]: You bind yourself to it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And the Buddha said something to the same effect, when he said it's because people take what's not theirs, what shouldn't be theirs, what cannot be theirs, as if it's theirs and they act out of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why the Mahārāja does with them what he wants, controls them, subjects you to all these things.
[SPEAKER_00]: What are the things that cannot be yours and shouldn't be yours and you keep taking as yours and that actually belong to mother, don't belong to you?
[SPEAKER_00]: It's your eyes and your sights, your nose and your smells.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, your very senses, the nature of them shows you that it's not yours.
[SPEAKER_00]: You ignore it, you automatically take it as yours.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why just turning a blind eye is enough in itself to result in the whole mass of suffering.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not like I turn a blind eye, then I do a second step of taking it as mine, then I do this, then...
[SPEAKER_00]: Turning a blind eye to the nature of your senses, for example, your eyes, your nose, your body, your life, means automatically, implies taking it as mine.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because if I ignore that it's not mine, I automatically imply that it's mine, that it's for me, that it's in my control.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then you keep acting as if it is your control, and that's how you perpetuate turning of the blind eye.
[SPEAKER_00]: You keep acting out of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: You have to stop acting out of it, and then stop doing it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Internally, stop turning that blind eye, start admitting it, go against the grain.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's why everybody can benefit from solitude, to the extent that they are able to to practice it.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, if you don't practice it to fullest end, well, you have to take responsibility for that as well.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you might find yourself already too far in life, whereby you can't, like, just
[SPEAKER_00]: Withdraw from everything, because there will be consequences, but that's no one else's responsibility.
[SPEAKER_00]: You are responsible for finding yourself in such situation.
[SPEAKER_00]: But now people realize that that situation, they can't withdraw themselves from it, so then they feel justified in avoiding responsibility for it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's completely extra.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, you might not be able... you have infants and whatever, other family members depending on you, so you can't just leave because they'll die.
[SPEAKER_00]: But that doesn't mean you're justified now in ignoring responsibility for that situation that you yourself built up.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, yeah, you can't ignore the fact that your choices brought you in these circumstances that now other lives depend upon you.
[SPEAKER_00]: But that doesn't mean you should take responsibility for it, no matter how late that responsibility comes, the recognition that responsibility comes.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's still better to take it, than to then ignore it further.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because who knows?
[SPEAKER_00]: Through taking responsibility, some new ways and options might present themselves, that you won't see for as long as you're avoiding responsibility for it.
[SPEAKER_00]: But people don't take responsibility, because it's too unpleasant.
[SPEAKER_01]: But yeah, taking responsibility, things become very clear, options become more...
[SPEAKER_00]: But, because you're too concerned about not experiencing discomfort, you basically obscure and limit all these options that you could have otherwise became aware of.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why you actually get more resilience, less subjected to suffering, through recognizing, through admitting, through taking responsibility.
[SPEAKER_00]: Initially, it's more unpleasant, but in the long run, it's actually far more pleasant.
[SPEAKER_00]: Far less unpleasant, let's put it like that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because if you're taking responsibility, you see where the problem is.
[SPEAKER_00]: And the problem is in avoiding responsibility.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why you suffer.
[SPEAKER_00]: So you suffer, not because a disagreeable feeling touches you,
[SPEAKER_00]: You suffer because you avoid responsibility for the suffering in regard to the disagreeable feeling.
[SPEAKER_00]: You start taking responsibility for that suffering in regard to disagreeable feeling, you stop blaming disagreeable feeling for that suffering, which means you stop resisting it, which means you stop suffering.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's it.
[SPEAKER_01]: You stop touching it.
[SPEAKER_00]: You stop touching it.
[SPEAKER_00]: You stop getting into the domain that doesn't belong to you, that belongs to matter.
[SPEAKER_00]: You stop taking it as yours.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's it.
[SPEAKER_00]: You cannot be affected by anything then.
[SPEAKER_00]: No matter how disagreeable.